<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise co[n]cernynge impropriations of benefices. Cum priuilegio regali</title>
            <author>Bigod, Francis, Sir, 1508-1537.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1535</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17421</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4240</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110964</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846408</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846408</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11372</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17421)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11372)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 28:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise co[n]cernynge impropriations of benefices. Cum priuilegio regali</title>
                  <author>Bigod, Francis, Sir, 1508-1537.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Tho[mas] Godfray,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Lo[n]don :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1535?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Line 1 of text on B3 recto begins: gregatio.</note>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures A⁴ B-C D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11372:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11372:1"/>
            <p>A treatiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernynge impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefices,</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>Cum priuilegio regali.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border featuring manicules, flowers, a dragon, a lion, an imp, birds and other mythical creatures</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:11372:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11372:2"/>
            <head>The preface. ¶ To the kyng our moſt gracyous ſouerayne lorde. Frauncys By god knyght / his humble and true fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubiect / and dayly oratour / wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth dayly augmentatyon and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace and honoure.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Dyd nat perfytly know (moſt gracyouſe / moſte chriſten / and moſt vyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) how that amonge all other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues / that the vertuous gyftes gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by grace onely / throughe the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of almighty god / of the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable gyfte of gentelneſſe and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manyte / dyd ſo habundantly / accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulately / and ſo manifeſtly poſſeſſe and reygne in your noble and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cely herte / tyll that nowe it appereth manifeſtly by your exteryour noble actes and dedes / for els vndoutedly I wold nat only haue ben a ſhamed
<pb facs="tcp:11372:3"/> ſo to attempte rudely / folyſſhly / and rather preſumptuouſlye to trouble &amp; diſquyet ſuch an imperyall maieſty with this my rude &amp; barbarouſe wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge / in the hynderaunce of youre godly &amp; ſpirituall ſtudies / with whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che your highneſſe taketh ſuch intol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lerable payne: as well to ſet forth the mere / ſyncere / &amp; trewe glorie of god / as alſo theſtablyſſhment / quietneſſe and vnyte of this youre chriſten co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men welth. But alſo in myne owne conceyte &amp; opinyon / callynge to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance my greate &amp; manyfolde in ſuffycyency in lernynge / to write vnto ſo mighty &amp; famouſe a prince / I ſhulde euen by &amp; by haue dyſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed myne owne behauyoure in that behalfe / &amp; iuged my ſelfe worthye of blame. But nowe conſyderi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge moſt benigne ſouereygne lorde / how mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che all your ſubiectes be imperpetu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to laude / praiſe / &amp; glorify almightye god / to ſende vnto vs ſo
<pb facs="tcp:11372:3"/> chriſten a ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to haue rule &amp; gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ouer vs yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ſubiectes / by who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe great &amp; ineſtymable dilygente la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour / charge / ſtudye &amp; payne / we be delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the harde / ſharpe / &amp; .x. M. tymes more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudicyall capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uytie of that babylonycall man of Rome / to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſwete &amp; ſofte ſeruyce / ye / rather lyberty of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel / I can for my part no leſſe do / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to preſent to your grace ſome thinge therby to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare how gladly I wolde gyue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes to your hyghneſſe / for ſuch ꝓfet as I amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge others haue receiued by this ſayd benefite i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our delyuerau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which acte is of it ſelfe ſo hyghly to the gret peace / vnyte / &amp; welth of this moſt noble empyre of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / that if there wer non other cauſe but that onely / we were bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to / &amp; with all our dilygence &amp; induſtry / to ſtudye / labour / &amp; deuyſe howe this benefyte excedynge all other / mighte worlde without ende be extolled / praiſed / &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:11372:4"/> made immortall / and to receyte how moch the furtherau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of goddꝭ glori is by the ſame acte ſet forth &amp; aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced / my lernynge ne yet wytte wyll nat ſerue me. Yet I dare boldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferme / pondering &amp; conſydering de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely theffecte &amp; cyrcumſtance of this mater. This acte is no leſſe worthe than wel worthy to be ſette in the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke of kinges of the olde teſtamente / as a thinge ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dynge to goddes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure / as moch as any other hiſtory therin conteyned. But what ſhulde I attempte or go about to expreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> condygne &amp; euerlaſtynge prayſes &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes / which your maieſty hath de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerued of all your hole cominalte for the benefytes before named / onleſſe I wolde take in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de lyke an euyll workeman / whiche by reaſon of his vnperfeytneſſe in his ſcyence / ſhuld vtterly ſtayne &amp; deface the thinge / he wold moſt erneſtly &amp; dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſhew and ſet fo: th. I wyll therefore moſt
<pb facs="tcp:11372:4"/> exellent emperour of this realme / ſet all this aſyde &amp; ſhewe to your grace the cauſe of my enterpriſe / for ſomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as I ꝑceyue that all your gracy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſe ꝓcedyngꝭ ar only driuen &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt high / iuſt / &amp; ſyncere honour of almighty god / the publy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke welth &amp; vnity of all chriſtendome moſt ſpecially of this yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> moſt noble realme of Englande / it hath anima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted &amp; encouraged me / accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmall talent of lerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that the lorde hath lent to me / to put your grace in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brane of the intollerable peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of imꝓpriations of benefices to relygyouſe ꝑſones (as they wyll be called) ſome to men &amp; ſome to wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whiche in myne opinion is a thinge playnly repugnant to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt holy &amp; bleſſed decrees &amp; ordynaunces of all mighty god / &amp; highly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> extolli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſupporti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / &amp; mayntenance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped power of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byſſhop of Rome / as your maieſty ſhall ꝑceyue in reding
<pb facs="tcp:11372:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:11372:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:11372:6"/> of this lytell treatyſe / whiche your grace nat beynge offended / I ſhall euer (god wylli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge) be able iuſtly to defende / &amp; alſo ſtop y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouthes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhall ſay &amp; abyde by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary and that nat w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> myne owne wordes but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> auctorities of holy ſcrypture. And further I do moſte hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly vpon both my knees beſeche yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> imperyal maieſty / that vnto ſuch tyme as this my lytel boke be clerely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futed bi ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke holy ſcrypture &amp; auctorities / as I haue approued the ſame / that it may ſafely go abrode vnder protection of your moſte gracyouſe and redouted name. And for the proſperouſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of your moſt royall eſtate of your mooſte noble and vertuouſe Quene / of your dere doughter lady princeſſe / doughter and heyre to you both (accordyng to my moſt bounde dutye) I ſhall dayly pray / my lyfe endurynge.</p>
            <trailer>¶ Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11372:6"/>
            <head>A treatyſe concernynge. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O recyte in one volume good chriſten reder / all the papiſticall captiuite ſeductyon / and diſceyte / wherwith manye yeres the kynges trewe and louynge ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes of this his moſt noble realme of Englande / pytuouſely haue ben deluded / begyled / and blynded: It ſhulde (I thynke) nat onely euen ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre the eares of all them that ben good and vertuouſe / but alſo be a laboure and burdeyne to great and ſtrange / for the lernynge of him that hath no more than I. Yea / &amp; though my lerninge were a great dele more paſſynge than it is / and myne elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as good as euer was Demoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenes / yet all were one. Excepte it be poſſyble / and any thinge lykely for a thinge that is infynite to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended of that that is fynite. Therfore for this tyme ouerpaſſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge
<pb facs="tcp:11372:7"/> ſo many thinges withoute ende and reaſon / that is / to detecte the fraudes and gyles of the foreſayde paſtyſtes / both all and ſome / which is nat poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyble. I ſhall be content at this ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to ſaye my mynde in one thynge partyculer / wherof hytherto no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I knowe hath any thinge ſayde or written / for a reformatyon to be had in the abuſe therof. My meni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge is of the craftye iuggelynge / cleane conueyaunce / &amp; lewde legerdemayn vſed amongeſt ſome men (ye knowe whome I meane) concernynge the impropriatyons of benefyces. Of all peſtylent infections that euer in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaded outher realme or regyon / the mooſt pernycyouſe and dyemeterly repugnaunte agaynſt the bleſſed or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunce of almighty god. Here nowe to boſte (as ſome man wolde that were a ioyly papyſt) that I am ſuffyciente to confounde &amp; conuynce
<pb facs="tcp:11372:7"/> all them that wolde withſtande me in this one argumente and cauſe / in dyſpyte of all their ſubtyll ſophiſtry and nyghe ſcraped ſcryptures / wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted out of frame / it ſhall nat moche nede / for my mynde is with no man to contende or ſtryue either moch or lytell: But playnly I entende to vt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce without either payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge or colourynge / ſophiſmes / or ſophyſtrye / &amp; after to leue the mater to the iugemente of them that ben in authoritye / and maye / whan it ſhall lyke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> well ſet a redreſſe / nat onely in this / but alſo in all other abuſes nat to be ſuffred. Neither do I mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che regarde the blynde reaſons and carnall perſuatyons / that maye be broughte for the defence of their fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation / wherwith here tofore they haue allured the nobles of this realme / to impropriate (as they call it) vnto theym ſuche benefyces: for
<pb facs="tcp:11372:8"/> truthe ſhall at length ouercome all their falſhed. Truth maye well be blamed / but it can neuer be ſhamed. Suche is thexellency and vertue of truth. For aſmoch than as the cauſe of it ſelfe is ſo heynouſe / that it can with no conſcyence any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered of any Chriſten ſtomake / but that it oughte to be reclaymed at / of all well mynded people / bothe with hert and ſoule. And for as moche as the truthe ſtandeth with me / both of good ſcrypture &amp; reaſon / that theſe impropriatyons be falſe &amp; abhomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in the ſyght of god / as my iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement ſerueth me / me thynketh I may right well without any ſuſpect of temerytie / or any other euyll af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectyon entre into the mater / whiche I entende and purpoſe.</p>
            <p>I thynke no man to be ſo blynde / but he knoweth that almightye god hath ordeyned in his faythfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:11372:8"/> of chriſten people / one ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall kynde of miniſters / which are bounden afore thadminiſtratyon of all ſacramentes / chefely and princy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to applye them ſelfe to the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere declaratyon and publyſſhynge of his moſt holy worde and goſpell this wytneſſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Paule by theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des: Non enim miſit me deus vt baptizarem / ſed vt eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelizem. Et alibi. Ve mihi ſi no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euangelizem.</p>
            <p>The lorde (ſaith he) hath nat ſent me to baptyſe / but rather to preache. Yea / wo be to me (ſaythe he in a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place) if I do nat preche. But what nede me to proue that men be bounde to preche / whan no man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth it? The thinge that we enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to proue / is to proue that impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priatyons are nat to be ſuffred / no / nat of a Turke / if he wyll haue his relygyon &amp; lawe to contynewe and floriſſhe. How moche leſſe than are
<pb facs="tcp:11372:9"/> they nat to be promytted of a criſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Thauctour of whoſe relygion is nother the pope nor Machomet / nor yet any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but euen the lyuing god / the god of all goddes / and the creatour of heuen and erth. Nowe if ye graunte me that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be bounde to laboure in the vyneyard of the lorde / and in the worke of his goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. I trowe &amp; beleue that it were nat moch agaynſt good reaſon / that a good workeman / and he that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth iuſtly for his lyuynge / had as he is worthy / and as reaſon and ſcripture wyll / a rewarde worthy / &amp; accordynge to his laboure. For the ſcrypture ſayth: Dignus eſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceuarius mercedeſua. A true work man is worthy to haue for his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. And I am ſure that the Turke for very ſhame could nat deny this. But let vs ſe more of the ſcrypture. Paule ſayth: Si nos vobis ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualia
<pb facs="tcp:11372:9"/> ſeminauimus / magnum eſt ſi carnalia veſtra metamus: That is: If we do miniſter vnto you thoſe thynges that ben heuenly and ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>al do you thynke it a high thinge if we reape and receyue of you agayne thoſe that ben but worldly and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſytorie thynges? And in another place: Quis ſuis ſtipendtis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litat vn<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>? Quis plantat vineam / et de fructu eius non edit? Quis pa ſcit gregem / et de lacte gregis non manducat? This is: Who goth a warrefare any tyme at his owne proper charge? Who planteth a vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyarde and eteth nat of the fruite? Who fedeth a flocke and eteth nat of the mylke? Se you nat here howe vehemente Paule is / in this that he wolde haue the precher to be honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly founde? Yea / and to thentent that all the world may vnderſtande how feruent he is in this mater: Marke
<pb facs="tcp:11372:10"/> alſo how he bringeth in the olde law for him / as who ſhulde ſaye: If ye were / or be ſo vnreaſonable to deny theſe authorityes and reaſons / that I haue here adduced &amp; brought in / as thynges inuented of myne owne braynes / &amp; as a new fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de holyday / deuyſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out authorite or counſell yet I trowe you neither wyll or can denye / but that longe &amp; many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande yeres before I was borne / or you either / it was well and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyallye prouyded of god almightye for his miniſters &amp; ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che laboured / or were otherwyſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyed at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement in his holy temple. Therfore (ſaith Paul) marke what the ſcrypture ſayth:</p>
            <p>Qiſcitis quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hit qui in ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rio operant / que de ſacrario ſunt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt. &amp;c. Do ye not (ſayth he) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande / how that they which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſter in the temple / haue their fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge
<pb facs="tcp:11372:10"/> of the temple? and that they whiche attende vpon thaultare / are partetakers of the aultare? Euen ſo (ſayth Paul) doth the lorde ordeyne that they which preache the goſpell / ſhulde lyue by the goſpell. And yet Paule here in thaduouchynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde ordynance of god / made in his olde teſtament / enforceth nat to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the payment of tythe / but all his dilygence is to iuſtifye his doctrine to be no newe lernynge / nor yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented of his owne fantaſy / but that in all tymes / &amp; all ages / god wolde euer his miniſters to be honeſtly ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyned and founde. Now this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmed / ſtablyſſhed / and grounded / as I thinke it wyl be denyed of fewe or none. I beſech you all my lordes ladyes / and maiſters of impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons / what other thinges ben your imꝓpriatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / than thinges directly fyghtynge agaynſt goddes holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:11372:11"/> agaynſte his holy wyll / a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſt his moſt bleſſed pleaſure / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt his holy ſpyrite? Fynally a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſt himſelfe and all that is god. And conſequently what can ye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of them / but thinges abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble / thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges deteſtable / playne thefte and robberye. Yea / and more than twyſe ſacrylege. I beſech you what do you call them: yea / &amp; howe moch are they to be hated / that ben but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen preuy pykepurſes? were he leſſe worthye than to be ſet vpon the pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary? But what of him that robbeth a man euen at noone in the kynges high waye? yea / euen in the myddes of Poules churche before all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes eyes? Be nat you my maiſters im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propryatours / ſuppoſe ye euen the ſame perſones: If ye be and haue ben ſo / euer ſyns you ſtale vnto you theſe impropriatyons / what wolde you ſaye / or what ſhulde the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours
<pb facs="tcp:11372:11"/> ſay? Shuld theft be let alone Shulde ſacrylege be ſuffred? ſhuld pykynge be paynted? Yea / and at fewe wordes ſhuld murder be main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayned? But me thynketh I here you whyſper that ye be no murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers / theues / pykers / ſacrylegyans / nor yet none of all this geare / No ar nat? Well / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſe well we muſt haue more to do with you. For as moche as ye denye the cryme layde vnto youre charge. Ye ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that good and vertuouſe men before our dayes / whiche loued the wyll of god / whiche loued his holy pleaſure / whiche regarded his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement / whoſe medytatyons and ſtudye both daye &amp; nighte was / to ſet forth his glorie / to auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce his bleſſed worde / and to maynteine the miniſters of the ſame / dyd (no dout of it) with the conſent of higher po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of kynges and of princes / and
<pb facs="tcp:11372:12"/> of their moſte honourable counſels / folowynge (in this behalfe) the olde lawe / for the moſt eaſyeſt waye and ſpedyeſt prouiſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / appoynt / aſſygne and ordeyne (for the ſame miniſters to be maynteyned) decymations or tythes / wyllynge and myndynge by this good prouiſyon / that within e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery congregation or paryſſhe / the miniſter of goddꝭ worde there / ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de be ſure at all tymes of a lyuynge rayſed and gathered of theſe ſayde decymations / and therein to haue added a certayne name / callynge it a benefyce / perſonage or vycarage / and lykewyſe turnynge the name of a miniſter or curate / to the name of a perſone or vycare. Furthermore orderynge that one man ſhall haue authorite / as patrone / to name this parſone / and ſo to gyue this ſame benefyce: albet / peraduenture that other in the ſame paryſſhe gyue as
<pb facs="tcp:11372:12"/> moche to the annuall lyuynge of the parſone as the patrone doth. Beſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des this / they ordeyned him a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to dwel in among them / to then tente that for his dilygente admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration / he ſhulde haue euery thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge neceſſarye for him within his owne gouernance: yea / &amp; haue it brought euen home vnto him / to dyſpoſe at his pleaſure / as it ſhall be moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedyent and neceſſary for him / that the more quyetly he mighte ſtudye &amp; apply him ſelfe to miniſter vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pure worde of god / &amp; to be euer redy at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to enſtructe them of all thingꝭ neceſſarye for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helth of their ſoules / and to be their trewe watch man and ſhepherde to take them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rauyſſhynge wolfe / and lyke a good trew herdeſman / a paſtoure to go afore them in ſpirytuall and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſe conuerſation: and euer wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be ſcabbed to anoynte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely
<pb facs="tcp:11372:13"/> with the ſofte and ſwete ſalue of goddes worde / all rancoure &amp; ſtryfe layde a parte. Nowe my maiſters impropriated or improper maiſters howe ſaye ye by youre fathers / haue nat you with your crafty colluſyon / almooſte throughe Englande / dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed theſe holy and godly prouy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyons / made for the mayntenance of goddes holy word / and for thadmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtratyon of this moſt bleſſed ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes / for the helth / welth / and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatyon of mans ſoule / for the vphol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge of the trewe and catholyque fayth / for the ſupportacyon of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue / and dyſtruction of vyce. Haue nat you (I ſaye) by the glykynge &amp; gleynyng / ſnatchynge &amp; ſcratchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / tatchynge and patchynge / ſcrapi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and rakynge togyther of almoſt all the fatte benefyces w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this realme and impropriatynge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto youre ſelues / diſtroyed this moſt godlye &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:11372:13"/> holy ꝓuiſyon / bereyued the peple of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god / of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trew knowlege of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tꝭ / of their trew beleue and faith in god the father / &amp; the blode of Ieſu Chriſt. For howe can the people haue any faith in god withoute preachinge? Howe ſhulde they haue any preachynge whan ye haue robbed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their miniſters? How ſhulde the miniſters ſerue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whan ye haue robbed them of theirs lyuynge? If the peple haue no faith how can they haue charyte? If they haue no charytie / what merueyle is it / if they ronne hedlonge and be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed from one vyce to another / from one miſchefe to another? Be nat ye thoccaſyon of all this? Who is elles I praye you? Haue nat ye the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations? Be the impropriacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons any thinge els ſauynge benefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as parſonages / and ſuche lyke? Do we nat ſay ſuch an abbot is par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſone
<pb facs="tcp:11372:14"/> here / ſuche a priour is parſone here? yea / ſuche a prioreſſe is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone here? How ſaye ye? thinke ye that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be foles? thynke ye that they ben aſſes? thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke ye that they ben ſtoc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes and ſtones / blockes and bones? Thynke ye that we vnderſtande no more reaſon than a greate menye of you do? Is nat this abhomination? Is this tollerable? Of all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſes / I conclude / that if it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye that the righte honoure and glorie of god be of all men (and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally by the miniſters of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che) to be preferred / extolled / and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted (as moſt worthy is) aboue all thinges and names bothe in heuen / hell / &amp; in erih: if his glorie (I ſaye) is onely to be ſought / if his doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemente to be regarded if the faythe in his onely ſonne to be eſtemed and valued / if his ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are to be reuerenced / if his ſhepe
<pb facs="tcp:11372:14"/> and lambes are to be fedde / and nat pyned / if the ſoule of a chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be any thynge worthe / if the holye ghoſt is any thynge to be deſyred / if all vertue and goodneſſe / if peace &amp; quyetneſſe are to be wyſſhed of / if al good men / if murther / blodſhedyng inceſt &amp; rauyne / with all other kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of inconuenyentes and myſchef are to be abhorred of all men. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſaye / that my improper maiſters and dames are to be diſpyſed of all men / to be aduoyded and fled of all men / to be ſhonned of all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / for that that they haue ben the vndoynge of all men / in takynge awaye / ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nullynge / abolyſſhynge of god and all vertues / of his bleſſed lawes &amp; goſpell / of fayth &amp; baptyme / and all other holy ſacramentes: and that for as moche as by theire improper im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations / the miniſters of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des holy worde and fayth / for lacke
<pb facs="tcp:11372:15"/> of lyuynge be taken from vs / which ſhulde enſtructe vs in all truthe and verytie expedyent for vs. But here ye wyll ſaye that we haue teachinge inough / and that there is neuer the leſſe preachynge for you. Whervnto I anſwere that in dede / if the mater be expended after youre affectyons / I thinke we had inought / although we neuer had no preachynge at all / for your mynde paradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture coulde ſerue you well inough / that we had as many prechynges as ther growe plummes in a peaſe wyſpe. And where ye ſay / that there be neuer the fewer for you: That is ſpoken euen as ſuche men ſhulde ſpeake: For in dede / althougbe we had prechinge &amp; techynge inoughe / yet for your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / as moche as lyeth in you / both god &amp; all preachynge / and all other holy thynges ben clene extyncte and rydde / and ſpecyally this holy ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce
<pb facs="tcp:11372:15"/> put out of the waye. But nowe ye wyll obiecte that no ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of god is broken / hindered / or prohibyted on your behalfe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this mater: For thoughe the benefyce be impropriate to a monſter / I wolde ſaye to a monaſterye / yet thabbot or prioure appoynteth a monke or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non to be the miniſter / and to preche the worde of god to the paryſſhe / who ſhall tarye and abyde amonge his paryſſhoners / and haue oute of the ſame benefyce a ſuffycyente ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge / and the reſte thereof to come home to thabbot and his bretherne: and this is no brekynge of goddes ordynaunce / but rather a turnynge of it to a better vſe. Wherevnto I anſwere / that where any ſuch vicare or minyſter is inſtytuted of his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot or priour / and trewly laboureth in thadminiſtration of goddes wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / it is nat onely well done to gyue
<pb facs="tcp:11372:16"/> him a ſuffycyent lyuynge out of the ſame benefyce / but alſo he were wel worthy to haue it euery whitte / &amp; as for the reſt that haboundeth / let him kepe hoſpytalyte / as Paule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth / or of neceſſytie wylleth him to do / and I ſaye / there ſhall but lytell remayne to ſende home to thabbot / and if he do nat kepe hoſpytalyte of the reſt / than is he a thefe / &amp; thabbot another / for the reſt is the poore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dygentes. But howe faythfull and dilygent ſuche men be ſo inſtytuted by abbottes &amp; priours to preache the worde of god / and how ſore they be therwith charged by their heedes. I thynke though I wolde cloke it / yet theffecte wyl nat ſuffre it. Yea / I beleue rather that they be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge perſecutours of goddes worde / ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the furtherers therof. I wolde I mighte in this poynte lye / but I am ſorye that it is ſo trewe.
<pb facs="tcp:11372:16"/> But nowe theſe men beynge neuer without excuſes / may peraduenture thinke this to be a good anſwere for me. We praye for the ſoules of them that haue improperated ſuch benefy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces vnto vs / &amp; ſynge maſſe &amp; diryge for them / &amp; ſet vp tapers for them to burne both day &amp; night. Whervnto fyrſt I ſay / that if a man demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of you an accompte to be gyuen of youre ſo doynge / aſkynge you who taught you to apply y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed maſſe that way / with the pſalmes and leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the diryge conteyned / and deſyred you to ſhew ſcripture for it / I thynke ꝑaduenture that ye might come ſhort home of a wyſe anſwere / which if ye can make / I thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke ther is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but he wyl be wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent ther with. Furthermore / we grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrypture co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth moch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praier of a iuſt man / but we be nat yet ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreed that ye be thoſe iuſte men
<pb facs="tcp:11372:17"/> of whom the ſcrypture meaneth. Agayne / albeit that it might be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed (as I trowe it wyl neuer be) that ye ben euen the verye ſelfe ſame men / yet whan wyl ye proue vs that ye ought to haue a lyuynge for your prayer. If ye come in and anſwere that: Oignus eſt operarius mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeſua. The labourer is worthy to haue his rewarde for his payne: We anſwer / that thoſe wordes were neuer mante in that ſence / nor of no ſuche labourers. And of this we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a good proufe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxiii. of Mat. where Chriſt rebuketh the ſcrybes &amp; pharyſeis eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſame maner of lyuyng that ye vſe / that is to ſay / by cauſe they wolde lyue lyke idle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes / vnder the pretence / that daye and night they prayed for the people to whom Chriſt ſayde: Wo be to you ſcrybes and pharyſeis: yea / but why? Forſoth ſayth Chriſt / euen
<pb facs="tcp:11372:17"/> therfore / bicauſe that vnder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and coloure of longe prayers / ye eate vp the houſes or ſubſtaunce of the wydowes / for the whiche ye ſhall be full ſore punyſſhed. Howe ſaye ye / might nat the ſcrybes &amp; pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſes haue brought in: Oignus eſt mercenarius mercede ſua / Againſt Chriſt? Thynke you they were nat lerned as wel as you: but they knew full well it coulde nat ſerue. Ye wyll ſay peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye be nat ſcrybes and ſome men ſaye / that ye loke as lyke theym / as a horſe loketh lyke a mare: and yet a horſe is nat a mare / nor a mare a horſe: but yet they be both of one kynde: and ſo be you ſay they and the pharyſeis. Here nowe lyeth the mater &amp; bledeth / you ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge at your negatiue / and they at their affirmatyue: Therfore howe might this mater be diſcuſſed? For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoth I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nat ſe but we muſt be faine
<pb facs="tcp:11372:18"/> to impanell a iury of .xii. honeſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But in erneſt / albeit that ye mighte as wel lyue by prayer as the precher maye of the goſpell / yet me thinketh that good honeſty wolde / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fyrſt ere ye take any money for it / ye made a good proufe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde were the better for youre prayer / and that ye could make men ſure to do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good with youre prayer / orelles I can nat tell what I ſhulde ſay. And againe in caſe ye mighte haue a lyuynge by the ſcrypture for your prayer / &amp; that ye were thoſe ſame good &amp; iuſt men / the prayer of whom the ſcrypture ſo moche enhaunſeth / yet I beſech you where haue ye that ſcripture that te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth you to take the lyuynge frome the prechers / &amp; to robbe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their lyuynges / &amp; the people of the lyuing of the ſoule / &amp; of fayth / charyte / and all goodneſſe / &amp; to lyue vpon ſtollen goodes? Some men that fauoure
<pb facs="tcp:11372:18"/> theſe newe founde ſectes / wyll per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture ſay: Well / yet it is better theſe monkes / chanons / &amp; ſuche lyke haue the impropriatyons (whiche though they preche nat / yet they ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe ſome hoſpitalyte) rather than the ſeculer preſtes ſhulde haue them / as they haue had before / which kepe no hoſpitalyite nor preche nother. To this it is eaſy to anſwere: That it is nat mete that any man what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he be / ſhuld receyue the benefyte or frute of a precher / onles he do his duty therfore. Qui adminiſtrat euangeliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ex eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelio viuat: That is / he that miniſtreth / techeth &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the worde of god / is right wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thye to lyue vpon / &amp; by the goſpell: and to preche he is bounde / if he wyl receyue ſuch wages / vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> payne of dampnatyon (as we preued a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell before by thauthorite of the ſame Paule) if he be nat let by god / that
<pb facs="tcp:11372:19"/> is that is to ſay by ſyckneſſe / &amp; if he do nat preche he is worthye to haue no penye of ſuche fruites / albeit he mumble vp neuer ſo many mate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes / Dauid pſalters / trentals / diryges / and ſuche lyke longe prayers / as we proued before wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſpake of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge prayers. For this is a good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: He preacheth dilygently and trewly: Ergo / he is worthy to haue therefore a lyuynge / and euen ſo is this: He doth neither of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ergo / he can chalenge no lyuyng: and this is Paules mynde / whan he ſayth: He that minyſtreth the worde of god / muſt lyue therby: excepte peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ye can proue that to mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble vp a longe payre of mattens be to preche the worde of god / whiche if ye can bringe to concluſyon / by my trouthe ye haue wonne the maiſtrye for me / for I truſte than / that whan I ſaye my mattens / that my mattens maye
<pb facs="tcp:11372:19"/> ſtande for a ſymple collation as wel as your mattens: and than I ſe nat but that an impropriation were as holſome for my bodye as for yours. And where it maye be obiected that ouer that / that the preſtes kepe none hoſpytalytie / they neither preache at their benefyces / nether come at them neither yet euer loke thytherwarde ſome of them: yea / and if it chaunce ſome of them to preache / it is ſuche geare / that it were more for the helth of his pariſſhens ſoules that he wer tonge tyed. Forſoth that is euen as trewe as the goſpell: yea / &amp; ſo trewe that it maketh myne herte wepe to thynke vpon it. I beſeche god ones to amende it whan his wyll is. Is it nat great pitye to ſe a man to haue thre or foure benefyces: yea / parad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture halfe a ſcore or a doſyn / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che he neuer cometh at / but ſetteth in euery one of them a ſyr Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lacke
<pb facs="tcp:11372:20"/> laten / that can ſcarce rede his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teus / orels ſuche a rauenynge wolfe as canne do nothynge but deuoure theſely ſhepe with his falſe doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / and ſucke their ſubſtaunce from them. Lorde / if it be thy pleaſure / ones haue mercye vpon vs / and gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue grace that we may haue ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medye founde for thys myſchiefe / bothe of impropriatyons / and alſo of them that miniſter nat the worde of god faythfully vpon theire bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyces: as they ought to do: for I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue knowen ſuche / that whan they ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue rydde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by a benefyce wherof they haue ben perſone / they coulde natte tell that is was their benefyce.</p>
            <p>This is a wonderfull blyndneſſe. And yet I thynke / ſuche or the ſame benefyced man wyll natte ſtycke to ryde an hundreth myles / to prycke a brouche vpon an ymage cote / and thynke it a righte hyghe merytori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe
<pb facs="tcp:11372:20"/> dede. But to ſuche tyme as it ſhall pleaſe the kinges moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable maieſtye / of his benygne mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and pytie / with his moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable counſel to ſe a reformation / as well for thabuſe of impropriatyons as for the incharytable demeanoure of all benefyced men / that be nat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydent &amp; abydynge vpon their bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices / there to do their bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duty. It ſhall neuer be wel in this church of Chriſt in Englande / wherof his grace is the ſupreme heed / nor yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe of goddes holye worde ſhall euer go forwarde in his righte tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and kynde. They haue yet an other abiectyon / and this is it: If impropriatyons be taken from mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteryes / ſay they / than coulde they kepe no houſes nor hoſpytalyte / but ſhulde be compelled to lyue all in po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uertye. Where vnto I anſwere / that as for pouertye it is their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyon
<pb facs="tcp:11372:21"/>
/ and ſtandeth with their own monaſtycall rules: for they all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the ſame at their fyrſte enteryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge into relygyon: yea / and it muſt be wylfull pouerty alſo / wherfore I can nat ſe by their profeſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but that they ben bounde to helpe to all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that ſtandeth with pouertye. And as for kepi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge hoſpitalyte with ſtollen goodes of impropriatyons / I thinke it can nat vayle theym but lytell to allege it / wherefore this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectyon is nat worthe a ſtrawe / and maye better be called an abiectyon / than an obiectyon. Beſydes this I knowe very fewe or none / but and if theſe impropriatyons were clene ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken awaye frome theym: yea / and a gret dele more / yet ſhulde they haue more lefte in their handes than euer had Benedict / Bernard / Dominik / or Fraunces / or yet Brimo: ye / more than many men thinke or can thinke
<pb facs="tcp:11372:21"/> well beſtowed vpon them. But &amp; a man might (ſauyng their pacyence) be ſo bolde with them / what mater were it (vnder correction I ſpeke) if all theſe improfytable ſectes / and ſtronge ſturdye route of idle paun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were a lytell poorer / to thende that the trew relygion of chriſt miȝt thereby ſomthynge be ſette vp and a vaunſed / and ſyffycient company of the miniſters of goddes true worde prouyded for in all parttes. I praye you / what an idle ſorte be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and brought vp in Abbeyes / that neuer wyll laboure whyles they ben there / nor yet whan they come thence to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens ſcruyce / in ſo moche that there goth a comen prouerbe: That he which hath ones ben in an abbey wyll euer more after be ſlouthefull / for the whiche cauſe they ben called of many men / Abbey loutes or lub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. And ſome ſaye that many of
<pb facs="tcp:11372:22"/> our holye fathers ſpende nat a lytell vpon my coſyn Iane / Elſabeth and Marget (ye knowe what I meane) inſomoche that / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they which be moſt popyſſhe of all / &amp; knowe none other god almoſt than the gret draf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacke of Rome / can nat deny this to be trew. Which popyſſhe ꝑſons nat withſtandynge wyll nat ones open their lyppꝭ to ſue for a reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the kinge our moſt ſoueraine lorde. And the cauſe why / as it is noyſed / &amp; as good ſygnifycatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ben therof gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen / is for that / that ſome ſuch abbot or priour wyll nat ſtycke to gyue an hundreth pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des at a clappe to ſuch a cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pyon to ſpeke in his fauour in tyme of nede. And I can beleue it well: for I ſe no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue mo ſure ſtakes to ſtande with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whan they haue any vrgent buſines than the monkes haue euen of them that knowe their noughty co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon
<pb facs="tcp:11372:22"/>
/ as well as I knowe my right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my lyfte. Now what ſhuld cauſe men to be ſo vntruſty in a mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of vntruth / let other men iuge. I can geſſe no mater or cauſe more ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely / than Huri ſarra fames (as Vergyll calleth it) that is: the myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheuouſe &amp; inſacyable hunger &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe of golde. And I fere me that euen at this day / money paſſeth faſt from marchant to marchant. A thynge there is in the wynde / what ſoeuer it be / that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knoweth nat of / which I truſt in god wyl one day come to lyght / as well as other thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gꝭ haue: for I dout nat but chriſt is true / which ſayth: Qihil eſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſconditum quod non reuelabitur. There is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſo craftely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueted but at the laſt it wyll &amp; ſhall come to reuelation. But what myſchef care they to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt if they may redeme it for money / &amp; may haue ſuche ioly fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes
<pb facs="tcp:11372:23"/> to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in euery corner? what care they for the loſſe of a lytel money / which they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> finde again in the ſore labour of their poore tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tꝭ How ſo euer the worlde go they loſe nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge / nor wyll loſe nothinge / nor wyll eat the leſſe by one cro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me or bit of brede: Be there neuer ſo great darth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde / yet wyl they me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure their meate by the bely. As ther was a blide abbot in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world which neuer wolde ſet hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe at dyner / but he wold fyrſt vndo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poynte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his bely / &amp; let it oute a certayne length / &amp; to ſuch tyme he had fylled his paukener to the poynt / he wolde neuer ceſſe as blide as he was. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde ſeldome make any ſouper: &amp; I thinke verily he neded nat moch. But to my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe / remoue me ones away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe materiall of all theſe inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenyentes &amp; theffect ſhal ſone be remoued. But
<pb facs="tcp:11372:23"/> as for to remoue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cauſe efficient fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them / that is / the ſpirit of the deuyll / it were very harde. For that can no man do but god / whiche can make a Camell to go through the eye of an edle: but as for the cauſe materyall / or their infinyte ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of ryches / of golde &amp; of ſyluer / maye ſoone be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued / if it pleſe our moſt redouted prince / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his moſt honourable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell. Take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them their i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>proper im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ꝓpriations with other ſuꝑfluytes / &amp; withi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a while ꝑaduenture they may be good men. And if nat that / yet am I ſure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> outwardly they ſhal nat be a quarter part ſo yll as they be now. It were wel done me thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keth that ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had their impropriations as wold do faythfull ſeruyce to god / to their prince / &amp; to their pariſſh / in pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chynge / ſetti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge forth ſyncerely &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely the worde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyuynge god: &amp; other that wyl nat or ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nat ſo do / it
<pb facs="tcp:11372:24"/> were beſt they were clerely dyſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched of ſuche benefyces as they haue what ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of bn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyces ſoeuer they be gret or ſmal / forked cap or plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e cap accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to. ſ. Pauls mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. Qui no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laboret / no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manducet. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyl take no paines / let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take no gaines: but if he wyl nedꝭ eate / let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nedꝭ ſwete / orels let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eate his thombes. Howe ſay ye nowe all my lordes / abbottꝭ &amp; priours w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your improper ipropria<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions? whiche of good congruence god put in your mynde ſo to call / as he dyd into byſſhop Cayphas mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ones to ſaye the truthe agaynſte his wyll: for if all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde had ſought a name for them / he coulde neuer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue deuyſed a better worde than im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations: for in good fayth they were neuer proper vnto you by the worde of god: but euen as fayre ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>len good as any is in chriſtendome. Howe ſaye ye (I ſaye) Haue ye any
<pb facs="tcp:11372:24"/> thinge to allege for you agaynſt my poore reaſons: if ye haue / come forth &amp; ye ſhall be herde. I wyll nat y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye lay for you / your olde ryueld refuge this dyd our fathers / there hath ben as wyſe men as there be nowe: why dyd nat they eſpye this geare? Tell nat me what your faders did / which were blynded w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch fathers as ye ben your ſelfe. But tell me whether your fathers i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo doinge dyd well or nat / &amp; accordinge to the ſcrypture or nat. And as for wyſdome I tell you agayne / that there is but one wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome / that we may ſurely truſt vnto which is the wyſdom of god lefte in his ſcryptures / if they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proue that their facte &amp; dede in gyui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to ſuch as ye be / was grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon this wyſdome / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we wil &amp; muſt nedes admyt it &amp; them to be wiſe / or els in thingꝭ perteyning to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule / we wyll approue no wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e
<pb facs="tcp:11372:25"/> but that. Thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke you this a good ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſay: Were there nat as wyſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before our tyme as ther be now? Ar ye nat a ſhamed of ſuche extreme madnes? I pray you tel me one thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Were there nat as great foles before our tymes as there be now? &amp; I beſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che you / why miȝt nat our fathers y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> made theſe ſame imꝓpriations be of that ſame ſorte. I ꝓmyſe you except you had the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition / that ye ſhulde trewly preche the worde of god for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I enſure you it was the moſt fonde &amp; folyſh acte (one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that euer was done: ye / &amp; a noughty acte alſo: If at the laſt it were their acte / &amp; nat rather your tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nouſe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation. But admyt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faders were wyſe both tagge &amp; rag / &amp; nat one fole amongeſt them / what than? is this a good argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? Our fore faders were as wyſe before our time as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be now: Ergo this was
<pb facs="tcp:11372:25"/> wyſely done? I pray you who tauȝt you ſo to reaſon? many a wyſe man ſomtyme may playe the fole / &amp; ouer ſlyp hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelfe? If he may / than (as the northen ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith) Gay layke you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your olde wyſdome / &amp; your wyſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And ſo helpe me god &amp; holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom / if yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> wiſe faders neuer plaied wyſer touches than they dyd in this behalfe / me thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keth you might aſwel a nother while allege vpon yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> wiſe mothers / &amp; what ſoeuer your faders were / me thinketh their ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes be nat the wyſeſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer I knew. Finally if thus moche may ꝑſuade you / that your imꝓpriations of conſcience ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nat be kepte any lenger. I beſeche you for the loue of god / if any drop of grace be in you / to gyue place to the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple &amp; playne truth which I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue here ſette forth / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out either ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilite or colours / as the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges wher vnto I neuer gaue my mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth
<pb facs="tcp:11372:26"/> to do. But if ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nat gyue place to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore reaſons here made / ſette your pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes to the boke / &amp; aſwel as god wyll gyue me grace ye ſhall be anſwered. And here I make an ende / nothinge medlynge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tronage of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeyde imꝓpriations to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhal be longe / nor yet with the perſones to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuche benefyces ought to be giuen / nor what ordre is to be taken about the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend al ſuch ꝑſels to them that be of more experyence &amp; lernynge than I / &amp; to them that be in authorite / as to oure moſt gracyouſe lorde &amp; prince / of all other pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces the moſt exellent &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy / &amp; to his moſt honourable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel to whom with our moſte vertuouſe quene Anne / &amp; princeſſe Elizebeth / &amp; all their honourable cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell / be lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge lyfe and ioye to the pleaſure of god.</p>
            <closer>So be it I beſeche Ieſu.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Printed at Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don by Tho. God<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fray. Cum priuilegio Regali.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11372:26"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
